Jane Ellis Papers, Inclusive: 1949-1998, undated, Bulk: 1974-1995
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Jane Ellis Papers
Inclusive: 1949-1998, undated, Bulk: 1974-1995
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
41
Ellis, Jane
12 document boxes
The Jane Ellis Papers contain materials produced or collected by Jane Ellis, the Keston Institute’s principal scholar on the Russian Orthodox Church in the twentieth century and a leading expert on the religious situation in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Jane Elizabeth Ellis was born on August 3, 1951, in Liverpool. As a teenager, Ellis became a member of the evangelical branch of the Church of England. After attending an evangelistic rally led by Brother Andrew, she became interested in the life of Christian believers in the Soviet Union. She taught herself Russian and studied Russian Language and Literature at Birmingham University. Upon her graduation in 1973, Ellis founded Aid for Russian Christians (ARC), the first organization that systematically provided material aid and spiritual support to oppressed religious believers in the Soviet Union. She served as ARC Director until 1986.
In 1975, Jane Ellis joined the Keston College (later Keston Institute) staff as a full-time researcher and analyst gathering and interpreting information on religion in the Soviet Union. By her mid-30s, Ellis had established a reputation as the one of the world’s leading authorities on the Russian Orthodox Church in the twentieth century and an expert on the religious situation in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia. Her most prominent publications included The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History (Croom Helm, 1986) and The Russian Orthodox Church: Triumphalism and Defensiveness (Macmillan, 1996) as well as translations of books previously published as samizdat. Ellis translated into English an original samizdat text about the life of Orthodox elder Fr. Zacharia. Written by one of his spiritual daughters and smuggled out of the Soviet Union, Keston published the translation in 1976 as An Early Soviet Saint: The Life of Father Zachariah. Ellis also translated and wrote an introduction for the samizdat autobiography of persecuted Unregistered Baptist Georgi Vins which was published in the United Kingdom as Three Generations of Suffering (Hodder and Stoughton, 1976) and in the United States as Georgi Vins: Prisoner of Conscience (David C. Cook, 1979). Her book on the history of the Russian Orthodox Church was translated into several other languages, including Russian.
Jane Ellis served as editor of the Keston Institute’s academic journal Religion in Communist Lands from 1981 to 1986 and the Institute’s magazine Frontier from 1987 to 1990.
During perestroika and until her death in 1998, Jane Ellis spent most of her time in Moscow where she established a Keston office. A deeply committed ecumenist, she played a key role in promoting a discussion between Christians of different denominations in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Scope and Content
The Jane Ellis papers cover the period from 1949 to 1998 with the bulk from 1974 to 1995. The materials focus on the history of the Russian Orthodox Church, the Church’s relations with other denominations, the lives of individual Orthodox clergy and believers, church-state relations, state policy on religion, and religious persecution in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Literary Works and Subject files are the largest series in the collection. Literary Works contains materials Ellis wrote and collected while working on books and articles, planning lectures and interviews, preparing conference papers, translating, and editing. The series pertains primarily to Ellis’ published works. The series also includes items related to unfinished and unpublished writing projects. Subject Files contains materials collected for research projects, including political and religious organizations, sects, religious freedom, Orthodox bishops and clergy, and Orthodox-Protestant dialog in the former Soviet Union.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received Jane Ellis Papers in folders with titles. Materials were organized into series according to their nature and topic and arranged chronologically.
The Jane Ellis Papers are organized into four series: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Works, III. Subject Files, and IV. Personal.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 41.
Related Resources
Related references
Walters, Philip. “Obituary: Jane Elizabeth Ellis (1951-98)” Religion, State & Society, vol. 26, no. 3-4, 1998, pp. 371—373.
Dennen, Xenia. "Obituary: Jane Ellis (1951-98)" Sobornost, vol. 21, no.1, 1999, pp. 55-57.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Ellis, Jane, 1951-; IAkunin, Gleb, 1935-2014.; Men)', Aleksandr, 1935-1990.; Ogorodnikov, Alexander, 1950-; Polosin, A. V. (Ali Vi︠a︡cheslav), 1956-; Regel)'son, Lev.; Vins, G. P (Georgiĭ Petrovich), 1928-
Subjects (Organizations)
Orthodox Eastern Church.; Russkai︠a︡ pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)' -- Clergy.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov -- History -- 20th century.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov -- Soviet Union -- History.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov. Moskovskaia patriarkhiia.
Places
Soviet Union -- Church history.; Soviet Union -- Religion.
Subjects
Baptists -- Soviet Union -- History.; Christianity and politics -- Russia (Federation); Christians -- Soviet Union.; Church and state -- Soviet Union -- History.; Communism and religion -- Soviet Union.; Dissenters -- Soviet Union.; Dissenters, Religious -- Soviet Union -- History.; Freedom of religion -- Soviet Union.; Persecution -- Soviet Union.; Religion and state -- Soviet Union.; Religious tolerance -- Russkai︠a︡ pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)'.
Genres
Biographies.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Manuscripts.
- Correspondence, 1979-1994; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains correspondence sent and received by Jane Ellis during her term at the Keston Institute. The most notable topics include an honorary doctoral degree for murdered Russian priest Fr. Alexader Men’, the True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church, and Soviet dissident Alexander Ogorodnikov.
  The series is in good condition.
  Acquisition Information
  Accession No. 41.
  - Correspondence: General, 1979, 1988-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Father Alexander Men', 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Alexander Ogorodnikov, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Viacheslav Polosin Interview: Evgenii Poliakov, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Russian True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church, 1980, 1983, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Invitations, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Speaking Announcements, 1983, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Literary Works, 1974-1996, undated; 2
  The largest series of the collection, Literary Works, includes correspondence, handwritten notes, draft manuscripts, research materials, and book reviews produced and collected by Jane Ellis while working on her books, translations, articles, and reports.
  The materials pertain mainly to Ellis’ published works, including, Three Generations of Suffering and An Early Soviet Saint: the Life of Father Zachariah (1976), The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History (1986), and The Russian Orthodox Church: Triumphalism and Defensiveness (1996), book chapters, and articles. Some materials pertain to unpublished or unfinished writing projects, including One Man's Witness: Select Writings of Anatolii Levitin-Krasnov and the English translation of Lev Regelson’s The Tragedy of the Russian Church.
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Chapters 1-3: Draft Manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Chapters 4-9: Draft Manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Chapters 1-3: Draft Manuscript: Copy, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Chapters 4-9: Draft Manuscript: Copy, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Edited Proof, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Introduction: Manuscripts, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Cover Proof, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Correspondence Pertaining to Publication, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Book: The Life of Father Zachariah: Reviews, 1976-1977, 1979, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Introduction: Draft Manuscript, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Part 1: A Family Chronicle: Draft Manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Part 2: Faithful Servants of God: Draft Manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Appendix: Draft Manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Reference Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Correspondence Pertaining to Publication in UK, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Correspondence Pertaining to Publication Abroad, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Reviews, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Testament from Prison Reviews, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Revision for New Edition: Manuscript, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Book: Three Generations of Suffering by Georgi Vins: Poems: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Book: One Man's Witness: Select Writings of Anatolii Levitin-Krasnov: The Man: Manuscript: Unpublished, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Book: One Man's Witness: Select Writings of Anatolii Levitin-Krasnov: The Churchman: Manuscript: Unpublished, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Book: One Man's Witness: Select Writings of Anatolii Levitin-Krasnov: The Polemicist: Manuscript: Unpublished, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Book: One Man's Witness: Select Writings of Anatolii Levitin-Krasnov: The Democrat: Manuscript: Unpublished, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Book: One Man's Witness: Select Writings of Anatolii Levitin-Krasnov: The Christian: Manuscript: Unpublished, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Book: Letters from Moscow: CCDBR Documents and Translation Summaries (1 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Book: Letters from Moscow: CCDBR Documents and Translation Summaries (2 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: Conformity and Dissent: Plan of Book, 1978, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Final Chapter Checklist, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Breakdown of Archive Materials into Chapters, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: List of Relevant Items in Files: Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Reviews (1 of 2), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Reviews (2 of 2), 1988, 1990, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Reviews: Correspondence and Clippings, 1986-1991, 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Reviews: Original Copies, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Reviews: Spare Copies, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Correspondence: Publisher Croom Helm Ltd. (1 of 2), 1983-1985 June (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Correspondence: Publisher Croom Helm Ltd. (2 of 2), 1985 July-1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Russian Edition: Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: A Contemporary History: Correspondence: Publisher Rutledge, 1988-1989, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Book: Voices from the East: Manuscript (1 of 2), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Book: Voices from the East: Manuscript (2 of 2), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Book: Voices from the East: Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Book: Voices from the East: Roster fran Oster (Slavska Missionen): Notes and Manuscript, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Book: Voices from the East: Roster fran Oster (Slavska Missionen): Print Copies, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Book: Candle in the Wind: Chapter "Religious Renaissance in the Soviet Union": Correspondence, 1986-1989, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Book: Candle in the Wind: Chapter "Religious Renaissance in the Soviet Union": Notes, Manuscripts, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Book: Candle in the Wind: Chapter "Religious Renaissance in the Soviet Union": Draft Manuscript (1 of 2), 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Book: Candle in the Wind: Chapter "Religious Renaissance in the Soviet Union": Draft Manuscript (2 of 2), 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: Priority Profile: Notes and Manuscripts, ca. 1986 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: Russian Orthodox Law: Notes, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: Triumphalism and Defensiveness: Chapter Three: Manuscripts, Notes, Reference Materials (1 of 2), 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: Triumphalism and Defensiveness: Chapter Three: Manuscripts, Notes, Reference Materials (2 of 2), 1989-1990, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: Triumphalism and Defensiveness: Chapter Four: Manuscripts, Notes, Reference Materials, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: Triumphalism and Defensiveness: Chapter Five: Fr. Gleb Yakunin: Documents, Clippings, and Notes, 1979, 1991-1996 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: Triumphalism and Defensiveness: Chapter Five: Fr. Alexander Men: Clippings, Notes, and Correspondence (1 of 2), 1985, 1989-1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Book: The Russian Orthodox Church: Triumphalism and Defensiveness: Chapter Five: Fr. Alexander Men: Clippings, Notes, and Correspondence (2 of 2), 1991-1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Book: Eastern Christianity and Politics in the Twentieth Century: Correspondence pertaining to contributing a chapter, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Book: Religious Policy in the Soviet Union: Chapter: Religious Policy in Practice under Gorbachev: Draft Manuscript, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Book: Religious Policy in the Soviet Union: Chapter: Religious Policy in Practice under Gorbachev: Submitted Manuscript, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Book: The Modern Encyclopaedia of Religions in Russia and the Soviet Union: Entry on Patriarch Alexis, 1986-1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Book Project: Russia: Chapter Eight: Christian Democrats: Reference Materials and Notes, 1988-1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Book Project: Russia: Chapter Nine: Untitled: Reference Materials, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Writing Project: One Man's Witness: A Day in the Life of Denis Ivanovich: Manuscript, ca. 1982 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Writing Project: The Tragedy of the Russian Church by Lev Regelson: English Translation: Manuscript, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Writing Project: The Tragedy of the Russian Church by Lev Regelson: English Translation: Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Writing Project: The Tragedy of the Russian Church by Lev Regelson: English Translation: Notes, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Writing Project: Crisis in Orthodoxy and Bozhii Liudi: Dartman, Longman & Todd: Correspondence and Notes, 1978-1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Report: Religious Minorities in the Soviet Union: Print Materials, 1973, 1983, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Report: Religious Minorities in the Soviet Union: Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Report: Religious Minorities in the Soviet Union: Manuscript, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Report: Religious Minorities in the Soviet Union: Notes and Manuscript (1 of 2), 1984 January (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Report: Religious Minorities in the Soviet Union: Notes and Manuscript (2 of 2), 1984 February (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Reports: Manuscripts, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Published Obituaries: Clippings, 1990-1991, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Published Articles: Clippings, 1977, 1980-1996 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Articles: Manuscripts, 1980, 1989-1991, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Book Reviews: Clippings, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Diary: Trip to Moscow, 1990 September 7-27 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Diary: Trip to the Soviet Union, 1991 June 7-July 31 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Paper: The Russian Orthodox Church: Triumphalism or Defensiveness: Conference in Granada, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Paper: Russian Orthodox Church's Attitude to the Situation in Ukraine: US Institute of Peace Conference, 20-21 June 1990: Manuscript (1 of 3), 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Paper: Russian Orthodox Church's Attitude to the Situation in Ukraine: US Institute of Peace Conference, 20-21 June 1990: Manuscript (2 of 3), 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Paper: Russian Orthodox Church's Attitude to the Situation in Ukraine: US Institute of Peace Conference, 20-21 June 1990: Manuscript (3 of 3), 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Interviews and Mentioning in Press: Clippings, 1988, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Subject Files, 1971-1997, undated; 3
  The second largest series, Subject Files, includes newspaper clippings, manuscripts, photographs, print materials, and correspondence pertaining to Jane Ellis’ research interests. The most notable topics include but are not limited to Aleksandr Ogorodnikov’s Christian Democratic Union, Russian Orthodox Church, True Orthodox (Catacomb) Church, Ukrainian Orthodox Church, Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, Orthodox Bishops, Russian Orthodox Church and Vatican relations, the 1989 meeting between Mikhail Gorbachev and Pope John Paul II, and Orthodox-Protestant dialog. Prominent individuals include Patriarch Alexii II (Ridiger), Fr. Aleksandr Men’, Fr. Georgii Kochetkov, and Konstantin Kharchev, the Chairman of the Council for Religious Affairs.
  - Subject File: Christian Democratic Union: Aleksandr Ogorodnikov, 1989-1992, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Subject File: Christian Democratic Union: Vestnik Khristianskoi Demokratii, 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Subject File: Christian Democratic Party of Russia, 1991, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Subject File: Orthodox Church and Religious Freedom in Russia: Collected Manuscripts, 1994-1997, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Subject File: Orthodox Church and Religious Freedom in Russia: Clippings, 1991-1996 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Subject File: Orthodox Church and Religious Freedom in Russia: Collected Book Reviews: Clippings, 1993-1996 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Subject File: Orthodox Church and Religious Freedom in Russia: Russian Orthodox Church's Greeting to Iosif Stalin, 1949 December 21 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Subject File: Orthodox Church and Religious Freedom in Russia: Viktor Aksyuchits' Speech: English Translation, 1990 May 29 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Subject File: Orthodox Church and Religious Freedom in Russia: 1997 Law on Religion: Correspondence, Documents, and Clippings, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Subject File: Orthodox Church and Religious Freedom in Russia: Collected Articles, 1995, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Subject File: Ukrainian Orthodox Church (1 of 2), 1990, 1992-1993 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Subject File: Ukrainian Orthodox Church (2 of 2), 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Subject File: Ukrainian Orthodox Church: Metropolitan Filaret (Denysenko) of Kiev, 1990-1993 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Subject File: Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church, 1990-1993 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Subject File: General Religious Conflict in Ukraine, 1990-1993, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Subject File: Relations Between Orthodox and Greek-Catholic Church, 1988-1993 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Subject File: Konstantin Kharchev (1 of 2), 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Subject File: Konstantin Kharchev (2 of 2), 1990, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Subject File: Ukrainian Greek-Catholic Church (1 of 4), 1989 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Subject File: Ukrainian Greek-Catholic Church (2 of 4), 1990 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Subject File: Ukrainian Greek-Catholic Church (3 of 4), 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Subject File: Ukrainian Greek-Catholic Church (4 of 4), 1991-1994 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Subject File: Pamyat. Anti-Semitism, 1989-1994 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subject File: Russian Orthodox Church: KGB Infiltration, 1992, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Subject File: Russian Orthodox Church - Vatican Relations (1 of 2), 1988-1993 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Subject File: Russian Orthodox Church - Vatican Relations (2 of 2), 1988-1994, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Subject File: Church-State Relations, 1989, 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Subject File: Gorbachev and the Pope (1 of 4), 1988-1989 October (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Subject File: Gorbachev and the Pope (2 of 4), 1989 November (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Subject File: Gorbachev and the Pope (3 of 4), 1989 November (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Subject File: Gorbachev and the Pope (4 of 4), 1989 November-December (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Subject File: Gorbachev and the Pope Meeting: Transcript, 1989 December 1 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Subject File: Holy Synod of the Russian Orthodox Church (1 of 3), 1989-1991 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Subject File: Holy Synod of the Russian Orthodox Church (2 of 3), 1991-1992 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Subject File: Holy Synod of the Russian Orthodox Church (3 of 3), 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Subject File: Local Orthodox Churches: Estonia, 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Subject File: Local Orthodox Churches: Latvia, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Subject File: Local Orthodox Churches: Moldavia, 1990-1993 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Subject File: Patriarch Pimen (Izvekov): Obituaries, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Subject File: Patriarch Alexii II (Ridiger): General, 1990-1994 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Subject File: Patriarch Alexii II (Ridiger): Election, 1990-1994 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Subject File: Patriarch Alexii II (Ridiger): Church Leader, 1991-1994 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Subject File: Father Aleksandr Men', 1990-1995 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Subject File: Father Georgii Kochetkov, 1994-1998 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Subject File: Sects: General, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Subject File: Sects: White Brotherhood, 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 14)